State University of New York, University Faculty Senate; Collection apap093
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York, University Faculty Senate Collection
1944-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap093
6.33 cubic ft.
The University Faculty Senate was created to centralize and govern all of the colleges throughout the SUNY system. This is an artificial collection assembled from the records held by University at Albany, SUNY representatives.
Administrative History
Prior to the establishment of the State University of New York (SUNY) as a system in 1948, most campuses had local faculty senates, assemblies, or other organizations. The University Faculty Senate was ultimately created to centralize and govern all of the colleges within the State University of New York system. The University Faculty Senate officially began when the State University Board of Trustees adopted a resolution approving the University Faculty Senate on October 8, 1953. With 26 recognized representatives from colleges in New York, system President William S. Carlson called the first meeting to order on December 15, 1953 at the Dewitt Clinton Hotel in Albany, New York. The University Faculty Senate by-laws state: "The Senate shall be the official agency through which the University Faculty engages in the governance of the University. The Senate shall be concerned with effective educational policies and other professional matters within the University" [The University Faculty Senate, State University of New York, 2001-2003, http://facweb.itec.suny.edu, 17 November 2003].
The Senate meets twice a year with special meetings as needed. University representatives of a state-operated unit serve a term of three years and can serve consecutive terms. To ensure that concerns and issues are resolved the Senate operates via committees. Some of the committees include the Committee on Undergraduate Education, Committee on Expanding Educational Opportunity, and Committee on Professional Rights and Responsibilities.
As the university grew new programs and policies were implemented in response to societal needs. In the 1960s the University dealt with radicals disrupting classes in order to get their messages out. The wages and integration of the workforce, specifically the construction crews on SUNY campuses, have been an ongoing issue since the 1960s. Affirmative action became such a strong topic for SUNY that by the 1970s Chancellor Earnest L. Boyer received letters charging reverse discrimination.
During his tenure, Chancellor Samuel B. Gould advocated communication between students, faculty, and administrators as a result of the civil unrest on college campuses around the country. In 1968, a conference was held on teacher-learner relationships in undergraduate education. Faculty, administrators, and students were invited to attend the conference. Officially called the Faculty Senate Workshop on "The professor, the student and the learning relationship", the conference took place June 17-18, 1969, at State Quad on the University at Albany campus. The conference stressed communication issues between students and professors. It was resolved that an open and honest line of communication would have to be established to successfully destroy views of professors in a superordinate role while students held subordinate roles. The conference advocated ending the ideal of the student as subordinate in order to prevent young adults from carrying that view of themselves into their communities and employment after college.
This collection includes information on how SUNY spent and invested its money as well as administrative functions. The meeting minutes of February 1985 indicate that the Senate resolved to cease investing in companies doing business in South Africa in order to express their disapproval of the policy of apartheid in South Africa at the time. Other issues considered during meetings included librarians receiving academic rank and privileges, salary issues, and other professional policies.
In 1991, recognizing the needs of a changing society, the Board of Trustees and the Chancellor of SUNY developed a new plan to prepare the students and the university for life in the next century. In order to reach this vision the university would have to utilize five basic principles. The principles were:
- To provide access to the university to a range of people seeking entry to public higher education.
- To concentrate on methods to raise the general knowledge of undergraduates especially their performances in math, science, and technology.
- To promote collaborative efforts between the university and government and private industry in the areas of applied and basic research.
- To meet the needs of the state by becoming more involved in health care, economy, and social welfare.
- To develop better management practices to handle funds received to subsidize the state budget from philanthropists, foundations and corporations.
The University Faculty Senate continues to provide leadership to the colleges of the State University of New York while providing a forum for representatives to discuss their concerns. Today the University Faculty Senate includes 45 senators as well as student representatives.
Scope and Contents
The State University of New York, University Faculty Senate collection is an artificial collection assembled from the records held by University at Albany, SUNY representatives to the University Faculty Senate.
The bulk of the collection is taken from the office of Professor Joseph L. Norton, covering the years 1968-1974, and Dr. Robert B. Morris for the years 1964-1971. Other University at Albany Senators represented include Professors Paul F. Wheeler and J. Ralph Tibbetts. Correspondence will be found in files for individual senators interspersed with other material, such as hand written notations, that was assembled from various folders originally labeled miscellaneous.
This collection documents the activities of the University Faculty Senate and the University at Albany Senators from the first Senate Meeting in 1953 through the 1998 session. Contained in these records are reports; minutes; by-laws; correspondence; published material such as newsletters; directories; overviews and handbooks. The collection documents the growth of the University system through booklets, brochures, master plans, and organizational charts held by the University at Albany Senate Office. Also of note is a draft copy of a 1977 manuscript, possibly by John W. Spencer, entitled "Origins and Development, State University of New York".
During the 1970s the University Faculty Senate became increasingly involved in governance and assumed an important role in the operation of the State University of New York. After the passage of the Taylor Law in 1967, the University Faculty Senate faced many decisions over issues of collective bargaining, and the changing relationships between administrators, professional non-teaching staff and faculty. These areas of interest are reflected in such documents as the Report of the President, Frank C. Erk, at the University Faculty Meeting (February 1970) and in the Report to the Faculty Senate by Chancellor Ernest L. Boyer (1972) as well as the correspondence of the senators. Collective bargaining documents from the office of the President of the University and various committees such as the Executive Committee, Governance Committee, Personnel Committee, and material from the controversy over granting academic status to librarians are all noteworthy.
Covering over four decades, this collection documents an expanding university challenged by social change and innovations in education and the work of faculty, in Senate assembled, to meet those challenges. Academic freedom, race and gender issues, student activism, and the need to develop programs to meet the educational needs of an evolving society are well documented in the meeting minutes, reports, committee material and correspondence of the University Faculty Senate. Of particular interest is the material from the Undergraduate Program Committee which illustrates the creation and development of the University-wide workshop, "The Professor, the Student and the Learning Experience", (1969) in which can be seen the process of creating, developing, and producing the workshop as well as analyzing the end results.
Of particular interest in the administrative files is the lawsuit against members of the University Faculty Senate in 1971 during Frank C. Erk's term as president of the University Faculty Senate. In the lawsuit the New York City law firm of Kaye, Scholer, Fierman, Hays, & Handler, filed a lawsuit against Frank C. Erk, et al. in order to receive payments believed owed to the firm. The case relates to issues with the Public Employment Relations Board (P.E.R.B.) and whether the Senate was an employee organization qualified to represent employees of SUNY under the Taylor Law. The Taylor law affects the rights of employees of New York State.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows:
Sub-series 1: Directories, 1953-2002
Sub-series 2: Handbooks and Reports, 1967-1992
Sub-series 3: Master Plans, SUNY, 1967-1975
Sub-series 4: Newsletters, 1964-1978
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by University Faculty Senators from the University at Albany.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Africana Studies; State University of New York SUNY, Central Administration; Education; Academic librarians -- Faculty status.; Collective bargaining -- New York (State); Education, Higher -- New York (State); Universities and colleges -- New York (State); Wages -- New York (State); State University of New York -- Directories.; State University of New York -- Faculty.; Universities and colleges--Administration; Foster, Arnold.; Morris, Robert.; Norton, Joseph.; Tibbetts, Ralph J.; Carlson, William S. (William Samuel), 1905-1994.; Boyer, Ernest L.; Wheeler, Paul F.; Spencer, John W.; Erk, Frank C., 1924-; State University of New York, University Faculty Senate; State University of New York. Faculty Assembly.; State University of New York News.
- Meetings, 1953-2001; 1; 3.0 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of minutes, summaries of proceedings, and a subject index. The majority of the series covers Faculty Senate meetings from the first meeting in 1953 through 1998. The meeting minutes contain information on the appointment of University Representatives by President Carlson during the first meeting, the drafting of the original proposed By-laws, and the development of different instructional programs. The minutes include copies of committee reports. The minutes also show the effect that the Taylor Law of 1967 had on the University Faculty Senate.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Annual Assemblies, 1965-1968; 1.1
    This sub-series is comprised of bound copies of the proceedings of annual faculty assemblies. With the first meeting in 1965, these assemblies were built around such themes as "The Role of the Faculty in State University" and "The University Student in a Changing Environment". Assemblies addressed such issues as the expansion of the State University, teaching-learning process, and educational television. In response to the demands of a turbulent decade, the role of disadvantaged students and the question of who shall be taught was the focus of discussion; other topics included allocation of resources, faculty research and community service.
    Arranged chronologically
    - Annual Faculty Assembly, West Point, NY, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 1)
    - Annual Faculty Proceedings, Syracuse, NY, 1966 (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 2)
  - Regular (Plenary) Meetings, 1953-1998; 1.2
    This sub-series consists of minutes of Regular and Special meetings of the University Faculty Senate, summaries of proceedings, and a subject index, 1953-1962.
    - Index of Minutes, 1953 December-1962 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1st Meeting, 1953 December (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 5)
    - Meeting Minutes, 2nd Meeting, Fredonia, NY, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 6)
    - Meeting Minutes, 3rd Meeting, Albany, NY, 1954 (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 7)
    - Meeting Minutes, Special Meeting, Albany, NY, 1955 January (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 8)
    - Meeting Minutes, 4th Meeting, Ithaca, NY, 1955 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 9)
    - Meeting Minutes, 5th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1955 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 10)
    - Meeting Minutes, 6th Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1956 April (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 11)
    - Meeting Minutes, 7th Meeting, Rochester, NY, 1956 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 12)
    - Meeting Minutes, Special Meeting, Albany, NY, 1957 January (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 13)
    - Meeting Minutes, 8th Meeting, Brooklyn, NY, 1957 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 14)
    - Meeting Minutes, 9th Meeting, Ithaca, NY, 1957 November (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 15)
    - Meeting Minutes, 10th Meeting, Farmingdale, NY, 1958 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 16)
    - Meeting Minutes, 11th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1958 November (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 17)
    - Meeting Minutes, 12th Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1959 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 18)
    - Meeting Minutes, 13th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1959 November (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 19)
    - Meeting Minutes, 14th Meeting, New Paltz, NY, 1960 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 20)
    - Meeting Minutes, 15th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1960 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 21)
    - Meeting Minutes, 16th Meeting, Oswego, NY, 1961 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 22)
    - Meeting Minutes, 17th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1961 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 23)
    - Meeting Minutes, 18th Meeting, Binghamton, NY, 1962 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 24)
    - Meeting Minutes, 19th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1962 November (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 25)
    - Meeting Minutes, 20th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1963 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 26)
    - Meeting Minutes, 21st Meeting, Albany, NY, 1963 December (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 27)
    - Meeting Minutes, Special Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1964 January (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 28)
    - Meeting Minutes, 22nd Meeting, Oyster Bay, NY, 1964 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 29)
    - Meeting Minutes, 23rd Meeting, Albany, NY, 1964 December (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 30)
    - Meeting Minutes, Special Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1965 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 31)
    - Meeting Minutes, 24th Meeting, Cobleskill, NY, 1965 April (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 32)
    - Meeting Minutes, 25th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1965 November (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 33)
    - Meeting Minutes, 26th Meeting, Stony Brook, NY, 1966 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 34)
    - Meeting Minutes, 27th Meeting, Brockport, NY, 1966 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 35)
    - Meeting Minutes, Special Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1967 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 36)
    - Meeting Minutes, 28th Meeting, Cortland, NY, 1967 April (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 37)
    - Meeting Minutes, 29th Meeting, Plattsburg, NY, 1967 November (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 38)
    - Meeting Minutes, Special Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1968 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 39)
    - Meeting Minutes, 30th Meeting, Oneonta, NY, 1968 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 40)
    - Meeting Minutes, Oswego, NY, 1968 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 41)
    - Meeting Minutes, Albany, NY, 1969 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 42)
    - Meeting Minutes, 32nd Meeting, New Paltz, NY, 1969 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 43)
    - Meeting Minutes, 33rd Meeting, Binghamton, NY, 1969 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 44)
    - Meeting Minutes, special Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1970 January (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 45)
    - Meeting Minutes, 34th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1970 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 46)
    - Meeting Minutes, 35th Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1970 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 47)
    - Meeting Minutes, 36th Meeting, Canton, NY, 1970 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 48)
    - Meeting Minutes, 37th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1971 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 49)
    - Meeting Minutes, 38th Meeting, Geneseo, NY, 1971 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 50)
    - Meeting Minutes, 39th Meeting, Alfred, NY, 1971 October (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 51)
    - Meeting Minutes, 40th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1972 February (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 52)
    - Meeting Minutes, 41st Meeting, Potsdam, NY, 1972 May (Box 1 (1-Meetings), Folder 53)
    - Meeting Minutes, 42nd Meeting, Brockport, NY, 1972 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 1)
    - Meeting Minutes, 43rd Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1973 February (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 2)
    - Meeting Minutes, 44th Meeting, Fredonia, NY, 1973 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 3)
    - Meeting Minutes, 45th Meeting, Oswego, NY, 1973 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 4)
    - Meeting Minutes, 46th Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1974 February (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 5)
    - Meeting Minutes, 47th Meeting, Purchase, NY, 1974 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 6)
    - Summary Minutes, 48th Meeting, Canton, NY, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 7)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 49th Meeting, Stony Brook, NY, 1975 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 8)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 50th Meeting, Binghamton, NY, 1975 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 9)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 51st Meeting, Ithaca, NY, 1975 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 10)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 52nd Meeting, Farmingdale, NY, 1976 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 11)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 53rd Meeting, Oneonta, NY, 1976 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 12)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 54th Meeting, Fort Schuyler, Bronx, NY, 1976 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 13)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 55th Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1977 February (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 14)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 56th Meeting, Plattsburg, NY, 1977 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 15)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 57th Meeting, Saratoga Springs, NY, 1977 November (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 16)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 64th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1980 February (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 17)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 65th Meeting, Morrisville, NY, 1980 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 18)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 67th Meeting, New Paltz, NY, 1981 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 19)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 69th Meeting, Fredonia, NY, 1981 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 20)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 70th Meeting, Binghamton, NY, 1982 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 21)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 72nd Meeting, Alfred, NY, 1982 November (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 22)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 73rd Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1993 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 23)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 74th Meeting, Oswego, NY, 1983 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 24)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 75th Meeting, Geneseo, NY, 1983 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 25)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 76th Meeting, Old Westbury, NY, 1984 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 26)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 77th Meeting, Canton, NY, 1984 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 27)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 78th Meeting, Purchase, NY, 1984 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 28)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 79th Meeting, Fort Schuyler, Bronx, NY, 1985 February (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 29)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 80th Meeting, Oneonta, NY, 1985 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 30)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 81st Meeting, Plattsburg, NY, 1985 November (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 31)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 82nd Meeting, Farmingdale, NY, 1986 January (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 32)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 83rd Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1986 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 33)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 86th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1987 April (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 34)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 87th Meeting, Brockport, NY, 1987 October (Box 2 (1-Meetings), Folder 35)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 88th Meeting, NYC, NY, 1988 January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 1)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 89th Meeting, Delhi, NY, 1988 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 2)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 90th Meeting, Cortland, NY, 1988 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 3)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 91st Meeting, Albany, NY, 1989 February (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 4)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 92nd Meeting, Potsdam, NY, 1989 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 5)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 93rd Meeting, Utica/Rome, NY, 1989 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 6)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 94th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1990 February (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 7)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 95th Meeting, Morrisville, NY, 1990 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 8)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 96th Meeting, Cobleskill, NY, 1990 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 9)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 97th Meeting, New Paltz, NY, 1991 January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 10)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 98th Meeting, Fredonia, NY, 1991 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 11)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 99th Meeting, Alfred, NY, 1991 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 12)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 100th Meeting, Binghamton, NY, 1992 January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 13)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 103rd Meeting, Syracuse, NY, 1993 January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 14)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 104th Meeting, Oswego, NY, 1993 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 15)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 107th Meeting, Canton, NY, 1994 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 16)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 114th Meeting, Albany, NY, 1996 September (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 17)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 115th Meeting, Farmingdale, NY, 1997 January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 18)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 116th Meeting, Saratoga Springs, NY, 1997 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 19)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 117th Meeting, Buffalo, NY, 1997 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 20)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 118th Meeting, Stony Brook, NY, 1998 February (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 21)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 119th Meeting, Brockport, NY, 1998 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 22)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 119th Meeting, Brockport, NY, 1998 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 23)
    - Planning Meeting, Albany, NY, 1998 September (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 24)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 120th Meeting, Delhi, NY, 1998 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 25)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 120th Meeting, Delhi, NY, 1998 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 26)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 122nd Meeting, Albany, NY, 1999 April (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 27)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 126th Meeting, Morrisville, NY, 2000 October (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 31)
    - Summary of Proceedings, 127th Meeting, New Paltz, NY, 2001 January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 32)
  - Summary of Proceedings, 124th Meeting, Buffalo NY, 2000, January (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 29)
  - Summary of Proceedings, 125th Meeting, Utica/Rome, April 2000 (Box 3 (1-Meetings), Folder 30)
- Administrative Files, 1944-1978; 2; 0.67 cubic ft.
  This series consists of reports to the University Faculty Senate, correspondence between University at Albany senators as well as material relating to the Taylor Law and collective bargaining issues. Also located in this series is information on the University Faculty Senate by-laws and the Board of Trustees.
  Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
  - Board of Trustees, 1960-1976; 2.1